<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>general on Brian Zhang&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/tags/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in general on Brian Zhang&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/tags/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Missing Heritability and Microaggressions</title>
      <link>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2018/10/missing-heritability-and-microaggressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2018/10/missing-heritability-and-microaggressions/</guid>
      <description>Missing heritability is like microaggressions: many seemingly insignificant effects can add up.
Two weeks ago, as I was taking a journey back to London Heathrow / Oxford, I came across a small connection in a journal article and a podcast. It was a nice moment of seeing two ideas click together.
The podcast, which came second, was an episode of Nomad, a British podcast discussing Christian faith outside the institutional church.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics / ML Books</title>
      <link>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2017/11/statistics-ml-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2017/11/statistics-ml-books/</guid>
      <description>At the start of the last post, I talked briefly about courses I’ve been working through. Here are some follow-up thoughts on good books!^[This post is strategically placed so I can cite some of these textbooks in later posts.]
This post will focus on textbooks with a machine learning focus. I’ve read less of the classic statistics textbooks, as I hadn’t specialized much in statistics until my PhD. However, these are a few texts that are on my radar to consult:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogging Aims</title>
      <link>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2017/11/blogging-aims/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.brianczhang.com/blog/2017/11/blogging-aims/</guid>
      <description>Hi there, and thanks for stopping by! In this post, I briefly introduce my current ideas for this blog and say a bit about myself.
As of September, I&amp;rsquo;ve been a first-year PhD student at Oxford&amp;rsquo;s Statistics department. I received my bachelor&amp;rsquo;s in Physics from Harvard in 2015, and after working for two years am excited to be back in an academic setting. Part of this transition means more freedom and a lot more self-structured learning time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
